<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: German | Thoughts and Data]]></title>
  <link href="http://askeluv.github.io/blog/categories/german/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://askeluv.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-08-06T08:45:30+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://askeluv.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alexander Svanevik]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How I Learned German in 30 Days]]></title>
    <link href="http://askeluv.github.io/blog/2015/08/06/how-i-learned-german-in-30-days/"/>
    <updated>2015-08-06T08:43:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://askeluv.github.io/blog/2015/08/06/how-i-learned-german-in-30-days</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This post is my summary of an experiment I started in January 2015: <strong>Learn German in 30 days</strong>.</p>

<p>Before starting, I feel obliged to list a few disclaimers:</p>

<ul>
<li>&ldquo;I learned German&rdquo; means I can have basic conversations in German, as well as understand German fairly well (both written and spoken). I have definitely not learned how to speak German perfectly.</li>
<li>I do not claim originality of everything in this text; I&rsquo;ve been heavily inspired by the writings of other language learners such as <a href="http://www.amazon.com/How-Learn-Language-Barry-Farber/dp/1567315437">Barry Farber</a> and <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Fluent-Months-Anyone-Language-Anywhere/dp/0062282697/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1425074701&amp;sr=1-1&amp;keywords=benny+language">Benny Lewis</a></li>
<li>My native language is Norwegian. This gave me somewhat of an advantage as it is linguistically closely related to German.</li>
</ul>


<p>If you want to learn a language as quickly as possible, you should keep reading. In addition to giving some general tips, and hopefully inspiration, I&rsquo;ve created some resources that I&rsquo;ll share in this text which will help you learn German fast.</p>

<p>I spent about 30-60 minutes daily in my 30-day period, so the time investment wasn&rsquo;t huge.</p>

<p>Now, let&rsquo;s get started.</p>

<h4>Five principles of effective language-learning</h4>

<p>I had an hypothesis that there are <em>five important principles</em> for effectively learning a language. One of the purposes of my experiment was to test if these were any good.
The five principles are:</p>

<ol>
<li><em>Set a clear goal</em></li>
<li><em>Speak from day 1</em></li>
<li><em>Focus on frequent words</em></li>
<li><em>Immerse yourself</em></li>
<li><em>Keep track</em></li>
</ol>


<p>Below I&rsquo;ll explain exactly how I used these principles to learn German.</p>

<h4>1. Set a clear goal</h4>

<p>I followed the <a href="https://weekdone.com/resources/objectives-key-results">Objectives and Key Results (OKR)</a> approach for setting a goal. My overall <em>objective</em> was to <strong>learn as much German as possible in 30 days</strong>. More specifically I wanted to accomplish these <em>key results</em>:</p>

<ol>
<li><strong>Learn the 1000 most frequent German words</strong></li>
<li><strong>Learn 10 German songs by heart</strong></li>
<li><strong>Be able to have basic conversations with my German friends</strong></li>
</ol>


<p>1 and 2 are nice because they&rsquo;re measurable, but the most important key result to me was number 3, which was a bit too vague. In order to make it more tangible, I booked a ticket to Berlin, and decided I should be able to spend the whole weekend with an old (German) friend, speaking only German.</p>

<p>Also, once I had decided that I would actually go through with my plan, I basically announced to the whole world that I was going to learn German in 30 days. The purpose of this was purely psychological, as I then would have to stick to the plan in order to not look like a complete idiot. In fact, throughout my 30-day period, people kept asking me &ldquo;how&rsquo;s the German study going?&rdquo;. To which I could always reply &ldquo;Sehr gut, danke!&rdquo;</p>

<p>(I also secretly decided I would record a video in Berlin speaking in German, which I did at day 29, but I&rsquo;ll spare you the awkwardness of the video I eventually posted on Facebook.)</p>

<h4>2. Speak from day 1</h4>

<p>I believe one of the biggest mistakes you can make when learning a language is to postpone speaking until &ldquo;you&rsquo;re ready&rdquo;. Language learning is like going to the gym: if you want to build muscles, anything other than exercising is just procrastinating.</p>

<p>Specifically what I did to speak from day 1 was to find some friends who either spoke German, or wanted to learn German. I then told them that I would be online for 30 minutes on <a href="http://appear.in">appear.in</a> every day at 8pm and gave them my own custom URL. I told them I would love to practice German with them there. I managed to get 5 people to join in total. None of them were native German speakers, though some were already fluent (which I found to be critically important!), and some were just starting out like me.</p>

<p><img src="/images/appearin_german.jpg" title="Speaking from day 1" ></p>

<p>In order to be able to stay in our target language (&hellip; German), and not revert back to English or Norwegian, I created a <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1TqjM4xdUVeFa32wjTSoswbZenozwz3DJAmzzbWoJZdM/edit?usp=sharing">Cheat Sheet</a> containing essential phrases. This sheet prevented me from getting blocked and generally proved incredibly useful in our online conversations.</p>

<p>Following the &ldquo;language is a muscle&rdquo; analogy, I also repeated out loud anything I heard or read in German when studying on my own. Compared to only passively receiving German, I think this really makes a difference for strengthening those German synapses in your brain.</p>

<h4>3. Focus on frequent words</h4>

<p>If you&rsquo;re not familiar with <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zipf%27s_law">Zipf&rsquo;s law</a>, you might be surprised to hear that only the 100 most frequent words account for about 50% of all spoken words in German films. Take a moment to reflect on this astonishing fact. This basically means that <strong>every other word you hear in a German film is a word from that top-100 list</strong>. The obvious conclusion? You need to know those words!</p>

<p><img src="/images/zipf.jpg" title="Frequent words are important" ></p>

<p><em>Illustration of Zipf&rsquo;s laws borrowed from <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/cowdung112/info-2402-irtchapter4">this</a> presentation.</em></p>

<p>I found a list of the most frequent words in German subtitles <a href="https://invokeit.wordpress.com/frequency-word-lists/">here</a>, and created my own <a href="http://bit.ly/german-top-1000">GoogleDocs spreadsheet</a> with the 1000 most frequent words. These words account for ~75% of all words in German subtitles. My simple task then was to fill out the &ldquo;meaning&rdquo; column for every word before my 30 days had passed. In other words, I had to learn about 30 words per day. I made heavy use of cognates from English and Norwegian in order to learn them, and I exported the words I had learned to <a href="http://ankisrs.net/">Anki</a> about once per week so I could make sure I didn&rsquo;t forget them.</p>

<p>The frequency list is one of the things I did that worked best. It served as a nice anchor that I could centre my learning around.</p>

<p>To test my vocabulary in the real world, I sometimes tried reading German newspapers or books, highlighting words I didn&rsquo;t understand. After reading a page or paragraph, I would count the words I knew vs words I didn&rsquo;t knew, then compute the ratio <em>words known / total words in text</em>. Towards the end of my study period, I would clock in at around 80-85% &ndash; cognates or context helping me push above the 75% I got from the top-1000 list.</p>

<h4>4. Immerse yourself</h4>

<p>Changed my Facebook language to German. Watched lots of <a href="https://www.yabla.com/">Yabla</a> videos.</p>

<p>But the thing that worked best for me was <a href="http://bit.ly/german-10-songs">my Spotify playlist with 10 German songs</a>.</p>

<p><img src="/images/german_spotify.png" title="Look how many songs I know!" ></p>

<p>Once I had learned the lyrics of these songs, I could play them whenever and be exposed to German anytime I could listen to music. I even recorded myself singing and playing these songs on the guitar. Again I&rsquo;ll spare you the embarrassment.</p>

<p>Picking the lyrics up from just listening to the songs is hard, so I would study the lyrics separately before trying to memorize anything. I used <a href="http://www.lingq.com/">Lingq</a>, which meant I had the lyrics available on my iPhone, and I could easily track which words were new when studying a new song.</p>

<h4>5. Keep track</h4>

<p>My <a href="http://bit.ly/german-top-1000">Top 1000 Words spreadsheet</a> was great for knowing roughly how many words I knew at any given point. Since I had the frequency of each word, I could compute the total &ldquo;mass&rdquo; of German that I knew &ndash; not just the total number of words, which I found to be quite motivating.</p>

<p>I also kept a simple diary in <a href="https://evernote.com/">Evernote</a> listing my activities per day. In the end there was only one day when I didn&rsquo;t do anything at all.</p>

<p><img src="/images/german_top_1000.png" title="Look how many words I know!" ></p>

<h4>Other</h4>

<p>I followed a course called <a href="http://www.rocketlanguages.com/german/">RocketLanguages</a>, but I only completed the first 3 modules.</p>

<p>On day 27, I started Duolingo and managed to test in at level 10, which I was quite pleased with.</p>

<p>I almost didn&rsquo;t do any grammar study, which I think was a good decision since I only had 30 days, and had no ambitions of speaking perfectly. One thing I would have liked to do in order to learn the German cases, though, is a set of 4 sentences of the type &ldquo;The man gave the book to the boy&rdquo; &ndash; one sentence for each gender + plural. Memorizing these four sentences would then probably have been a lot easier than trying to remember a case table.</p>

<h4>Conclusion</h4>

<p>Having concluded the experiment I would say I reached my goal.</p>

<p>I learned the 1000 most frequent words (and probably some more that I didn&rsquo;t track).
<img src="/images/german_1000words_learned.png" title="Learning 1000 words" ></p>

<p>I learned 10 German songs by heart.
<img src="/images/german_spotify_lingq.png" title="Learning 10 songs" ></p>

<p>And finally, I went to Berlin and had a great weekend with my friend Daniel &ndash; in German. He even taught me how to fly a kite:
<img src="/images/german_in_berlin.png" title="German kite" ></p>

<p>If you want to do a similar exercise yourself, here&rsquo;s a table summarizing my approach:</p>

<p><img src="/images/german_principles_in_practice.png" title="Principles in practice" ></p>

<p>That&rsquo;s it! Either this gave you some inspiration to start your own 30-day language adventure or you think I&rsquo;m insane. In any case, let me know what you think of my experiment!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
