<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Happiness | Thoughts and Data]]></title>
  <link href="http://askeluv.github.io/blog/categories/happiness/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://askeluv.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-11-12T19:31:45+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://askeluv.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alexander Svanevik]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Map Your Way to Happiness]]></title>
    <link href="http://askeluv.github.io/blog/2015/11/12/map-your-way-to-happiness/"/>
    <updated>2015-11-12T19:30:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://askeluv.github.io/blog/2015/11/12/map-your-way-to-happiness</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Here&rsquo;s an idea. Every single activity in life can be scored along two axes:</p>

<ol>
<li>How it makes you feel <em>in the moment</em></li>
<li>How it will impact your life <em>in the future</em></li>
</ol>


<p>Let me borrow some Greek words, and abuse some philosophical terms, by calling these two axes <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Poiesis">praxis</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Poiesis">poiesis</a>.</p>

<p>I recently scored activities in my own life according to this simple system.</p>

<p>This is the result:</p>

<p><img src="/images/HappyMap.png" title="My Happy Map" ></p>

<p>OK, I don&rsquo;t do heroin. And I don&rsquo;t have any parents-in-law. But these is my perceived, subjective scoring of these activities. It&rsquo;s my <em>Happy Map</em>.</p>

<p>Now, let us journey through the <em>five distinct lands</em> of the Happy Map.</p>

<p>We start in the South-West (or lower left). Here we find things that are bad for me in the long run that also make me feel bad when I do them. Things like worrying, complaining, and smoking. This is not a place I want to be, so let me call this place <em>Mordor</em>.</p>

<p><img src="/images/HappyMapMordor.png" title="Mordor" ></p>

<p>Next, we move towards North-East, away from pain and misery. We arrive in the centre of the Happy Map, in a place where I am &hellip; nothing. Not happy, not sad. Not developing, but not harming myself (significantly) either. I&rsquo;m on Facebook. I&rsquo;m procrastinating. I&rsquo;m watching TV. I&rsquo;m numb. This is <em>Wasteland</em>. This place has a strange gravitational pull, even if it&rsquo;s void of any mass or content.</p>

<p><img src="/images/HappyMapWasteland.png" title="Wasteland" ></p>

<p>It&rsquo;s hard to leave Wasteland, but eventually I feel like I have to do something with my life, so I travel North-West. Accomplishing things surely means sacrifice. No pain, no gain. I do interval training to get in shape. I work long hours at the office to build my career. I am investing in myself in <em>Ambitious Masochist Land</em>. Only the guys at Wall Street are North-West of me.</p>

<p><img src="/images/HappyMapAmbitiousMasochistLand.png" title="Ambitious Masochist Land" ></p>

<p>After putting in 14 hours a day at work during the week, I&rsquo;ve had enough. It&rsquo;s Friday, and I&rsquo;m heading down to <em>Sin City</em>. One beer is not enough, I need ten. If it weren&rsquo;t for my last drop of reason, I&rsquo;d probably be at the South-Eastern edge of the world shooting heroin.</p>

<p><img src="/images/HappyMapSinCity.png" title="Sin City" ></p>

<p>The next day is awful. I start thinking about my life. What makes me happy? I mean truly, profoundly happy &ndash; both in the moment and in the long term. Creating things. Reading. Learning about the world. Writing. Spending time with the people you love. Having good conversations with interesting people. Traveling. Laughing.</p>

<p>These are the things that I find in the <em>State of Zen</em>. That&rsquo;s where I want to spend my time.</p>

<p><img src="/images/HappyMapStateofZen.png" title="State of Zen" ></p>

<p><strong>Create your own Happy Map <a href="http://bit.ly/the-happy-map">here</a> and tell me what&rsquo;s in your State of Zen in the comment field below.</strong></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
