<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Thoughts and Data]]></title>
  <link href="http://askeluv.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://askeluv.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-07-22T21:51:42+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://askeluv.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alexander Svanevik]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[6 Things I Use Evernote For]]></title>
    <link href="http://askeluv.github.io/blog/2014/04/06/6-things-i-use-evernote-for/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-06T12:44:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://askeluv.github.io/blog/2014/04/06/6-things-i-use-evernote-for</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I use Evernote for &ldquo;Personal Information Management&rdquo; (PIM) aka &ldquo;keeping track of things in your life&rdquo;. Simply put, Evernote is essentially an extension of my brain.</p>

<p>I have two basic requirements for a PIM system:</p>

<ol>
<li>It must be fast and easy to <em>store</em> information</li>
<li>It must be fast and easy to <em>retrieve</em> information</li>
</ol>


<p>Based on these requirements, Evernote is the best PIM tool I&rsquo;ve come across. Still, many people find it difficult to get off the ground with Evernote, so I thought I&rsquo;d share some ideas that I&rsquo;ve built up over the last few months.</p>

<p>Here are <em>6 things I use Evernote for</em>:</p>

<p><strong>1. Physical-notebook substitute</strong></p>

<p>The obvious one. I used to carry Moleskines around, mainly to jot down ideas. In some situations I still do, but now I never have to worry about remembering to bring one with me, and where to store it when I&rsquo;m out of pages.</p>

<p><strong>2. Storing things I find online</strong></p>

<p>Articles, tables, graphs, anything! Just use the <a href="http://evernote.com/webclipper/">Web Clipper plugin</a> and you&rsquo;ll save it in a flash. Recently, I was reading up on <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Classified_advertising">classified advertising</a>, and every article I found on the topic, I tagged with &ldquo;classifieds&rdquo; (in addition to other relevant tags for the article). Now I have a small research bank with highlighted articles on the topic, which I can re-visit when I need to. Again: simple to store, simple to retrieve.</p>

<p>Also, very often I find articles I don&rsquo;t have time to read. Evernote Web Clipper solves this for me in a nice way: Clip, then tag the article with &ldquo;to read&rdquo; (plus other relevant tags), and change the tag to &ldquo;read&rdquo; when you&rsquo;ve read it.</p>

<p><strong>3. Digitizing paper documents</strong></p>

<p>Typical scenario: Find letter in post box. Rip it open. Skim it. Take a photo. Store in Evernote. Tag it. Maybe add a reminder. Then the best part: <em>throw the letter away</em>. Ah. Doesn&rsquo;t that feel nice?!</p>

<p><strong>4. Todos</strong></p>

<p>Evernote is not great for todos in itself, but here&rsquo;s the method I use on my work laptop. Have one note per week, and simply copy that note every new week, moving things you didn&rsquo;t get done last week over to your new note. Here&rsquo;s an example:
<img src="http://askeluv.github.io/images/EvernoteTODO_Example.png" title="TODO example" ></p>

<p>A nice bonus feature if you have a tablet: try the presentation view of your last week&rsquo;s completed tasks. Your accomplishments have never looked better!</p>

<p><strong>5. Language learning</strong></p>

<p>I also use Evernote to build vocabulary in foreign languages. The method is simple: again, create one note per week (e.g. &ldquo;French Vocab Week 16&rdquo;), and add new words as you go! Example:
<img src="http://askeluv.github.io/images/EvernoteLanguage_Example.png" title="Language example" ></p>

<p>It&rsquo;s a nice way to <em>situate</em> your learning &ndash; that is, you&rsquo;ll be able to register when and where you learned a given word. You can also easily keep track of your learning goals: how many new words did I learn last week, etc.. Also, you can set reminders to notes so you revise the words you jot down.</p>

<p><strong>6. Journal keeping</strong></p>

<p>I&rsquo;m not able to do one entry per day, but if I have 10 minutes to spare at the end of the day, I sometimes spend those minutes on a journal entry. There are a few Evernote journal apps around, but I&rsquo;m fine with just using the title to timestamp my note, then tagging it with &ldquo;journal&rdquo;.</p>

<p><strong>Bonus: Procrastination</strong></p>

<p>Think about it, if you accept you will have some amount of procrastination in your life, why not do something useful? I have tags for retrieving content from my Evernote when I&rsquo;m bored. I already mentioned &ldquo;to read&rdquo;, but &ldquo;ideas&rdquo; is another good one. Reading your own ideas and developing them further is obviously good fun. If you&rsquo;re learning a new language, &ldquo;vocab week&rdquo; is another good tag to have when you&rsquo;d normally be wasting time on your smartphone.</p>

<p><strong>Summary</strong></p>

<p>The common theme of the things listed above is that they all give me a better conscience. I worry less about ideas going lost, not finding useful web content again, letters needing archiving, tasks being forgotten, not spending enough time building vocabulary, my journal being empty, and precious time being wasted on mindless smartphone fiddling.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve mentioned some things I use Evernote for, and I hope you&rsquo;ve learned something useful from reading this. I would love to hear your favourite Evernote tips, so: What do you use Evernote for?</p>

<p><em>Fun fact: this blog post was written on my iPhone while flying from Oslo to Frankfurt using &hellip; Evernote, of course.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[List of Companies Who Provide Data Quality as a Service]]></title>
    <link href="http://askeluv.github.io/blog/2014/03/18/data-quality-providers/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-18T21:15:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://askeluv.github.io/blog/2014/03/18/data-quality-providers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Data Quality is important. However, most companies consider activities such as validating postal addresses and identifying duplicates to be outside of their core business. Luckily, investing in software and building up an internal DQ team isn&rsquo;t the only option to improve Data Quality. In many cases, it makes sense to instead have Data Quality as a Service (DQaaS).</p>

<p>Below you&rsquo;ll find a short (but growing) list of companies who offer Data Quality as a service. If you know of any companies who should be added to the list, feel free to <a href="https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?source=webclient&amp;text=%40ASvanevik+%23DQaaS">tweet me your suggestion</a>.</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://acuate.com/">Acuate</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.boaweb.com/products/data-quality-as-a-service/">BackOffice Associates</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.bisnode.com/International/Products-Solutions/Verify-and-enhance/File-cleaningpreservation/International-Data-Quality--myDQ/">Bisnode</a></li>
<li><a href="http://instantdq.com/">iDQ</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.informaticacloud.com/cloud-dq">Informatica</a></li>
<li><a href="http://iper.no/?lang=en">Iper Direkte</a></li>
<li><a href="http://ixsight.com/">Ixsight Technologies</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.pb.com/software/Data-Management-and-Quality/">Pitney Bowes</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.serviceobjects.com/">Service Objects</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.trilliumsoftware.com/home/technology/data-quality-solutions/service/">Trillium Software</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.uniserv.com/en/">Uniserv</a></li>
</ul>


<p>Do you know of any companies providing Data Quality as a service?</p>

<p><em>Disclaimer: I do not guarantee for the ability or service level of any of the companies above. You should of course make your own investigations to see if a given provider will fit with your requirements &ndash; or seek advise to make those investigations.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Word2vec: Deep Learning Language]]></title>
    <link href="http://askeluv.github.io/blog/2013/08/27/word2vec-deep-learning-language/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-27T22:13:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://askeluv.github.io/blog/2013/08/27/word2vec-deep-learning-language</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Introducing word2vec</strong></p>

<p>This month, Google open sourced a tool called <a href="https://code.google.com/p/word2vec/">word2vec</a>, described as a &ldquo;tool for computing continuous distributed representations of words&rdquo;, or in the words of <a href="http://gigaom.com/2013/08/16/were-on-the-cusp-of-deep-learning-for-the-masses-you-can-thank-google-later/">Derrick Harris</a> &ldquo;prepackaged deep-learning software designed to understand the relationships between words with no human guidance&rdquo;. You can read more about word2vec in <a href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/netapp/2013/08/19/what-is-deep-learning/">Forbes</a> and on <a href="http://google-opensource.blogspot.co.uk/2013/08/learning-meaning-behind-words.html">Google&rsquo;s blog</a>.
Now, you might already find those descriptions motivation enough to take word2vec for a spin, but if not, here&rsquo;s a concrete example on what word2vec is capable of. Using word2vec, your computer can learn a representation of words where the following two analogical relationships are true:</p>

<p>king &ndash; man + woman = queen</p>

<p>Paris &ndash; France + Italy = Rome</p>

<p>&hellip;Without being explicitly told to look for them! Specifically, word2vec gives you numerical representations of words, in the form of vectors, so that every word lives in a high-dimensional space, and can be compared by distance in that space (along the different dimensions). This itself isn&rsquo;t new; <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Latent_Dirichlet_allocation">Latent Dirichlet Allocation</a> also does this, but the way this space is constructed, is.</p>

<p>Now, why would we want numerical representations of words in the first place?</p>

<p><strong>Text is hard, numbers are easy</strong></p>

<p>Firstly, if you&rsquo;ve ever worked with text as a data scientist, you&rsquo;ll know that it&rsquo;s hard. Depending on your task, you&rsquo;ll run into all sorts of problems getting useful information out of text only using a computer (and not your own brain &ndash; that&rsquo;s cheating!).</p>

<p>Secondly, numbers are easy. You can find relationships in them, measure correlations, derive new numbers from them, visualise them, and so on. So obviously, converting words into numbers is a good idea!</p>

<p>In a way, it sounds ironic that text is hard, since as human beings we communicate through text everyday (in fact, it&rsquo;s a good example of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moravec's_paradox">Moravec&rsquo;s paradox</a>)! However, when you let your computer at a piece of text, it doesn&rsquo;t really have any conceptual framework to put the text into, and thus never really gets off the ground in understanding it. Word2vec is a step in the right direction to give your computer that missing conceptual framework.</p>

<p><strong>Using word2vec</strong></p>

<p>If we&rsquo;re doing predictive modeling, say, in a <a href="http://www.kaggle.com/">Kaggle competition</a>, we&rsquo;re generally trying to take some input data (say, your age and sex) and predict some output variable (e.g. the probability that you&rsquo;ll crash your car in the next year). Now, if your input data were your diary (in some horrible world where insurance companies secretly read your diary), how could a computer use that to determine your crash probability &ndash; assuming you can&rsquo;t just read them all manually?</p>

<p>Step one would be to deduce useful features from your diary. The simplest features would be simple statistical ones such as how long entries your write on average, how often you write entries, how many different words you use, etc. The more interesting ones would be based on the content of your entries. This is where word2vec comes in. With word2vec, every word in your journal is a data point.</p>

<p>What use cases for word2vec do you see?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Startup Engineering]]></title>
    <link href="http://askeluv.github.io/blog/2013/06/19/startup-engineering/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-19T13:51:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://askeluv.github.io/blog/2013/06/19/startup-engineering</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I just enrolled in Coursera&rsquo;s course <a href="https://www.coursera.org/course/startup">Startup Engineering</a>, which looks really good. The course is held by <a href="https://www.coursera.org/instructor/balajis">Balaji S. Srinivasan</a> and <a href="https://www.coursera.org/instructor/vijaypande">Vijay S. Pande</a> at Stanford University.</p>

<p>My main reasons for signing up to the course were to learn more about JavaScript-based technologies like node.js, and more generally to fill gaps in my own knowledge related to best practices in web development.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve only seen the videos for the first lecture, but so far it looks good. I was positively surprised by Srinivasans notes on the history of startups, connecting the decline of the Soviet Union to the Internet Startups of the 1990s. In other words, it seems like the course will have a fairly broad horizon &ndash; it&rsquo;s not just about technology. Srinivasan himself stated it will be 50% technology and 50% &ldquo;philosophy&rdquo;.</p>

<p>I encourage you to <a href="https://www.coursera.org/course/startup">check out the course</a>, which will be running until August 2013. You can find my public GoogleDrive notes for the course <a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1ioM7L3XYg1Ud6q3s6m8DjAT0AZbwzZrWjJvpY7l0FYY/edit?usp=sharing">here</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Entering the Blogosphere]]></title>
    <link href="http://askeluv.github.io/blog/2013/06/10/entering-the-blogosphere/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-10T23:36:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://askeluv.github.io/blog/2013/06/10/entering-the-blogosphere</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Right, I&rsquo;ve finally managed to set up a blog again. Visit back in a while, and expect great things to come!</p>

<p>In the meantime, have a look at these two helpful links here if you&rsquo;re keen on setting up your own <a href="http://octopress.org/">Octopress blog</a>:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://robdodson.me/blog/2012/04/30/custom-domain-with-octopress-and-github-pages/">Custom Domain With Octopress and Github Pages</a></li>
<li><a href="http://support.mashery.com/docs/customizing_your_portal/Markdown_Cheat_Sheet">Markdown</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
