<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Music | Thoughts and Data]]></title>
  <link href="http://askeluv.github.io/blog/categories/music/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://askeluv.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-11-12T19:30:22+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://askeluv.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alexander Svanevik]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Using Music To Learn A Foreign Language]]></title>
    <link href="http://askeluv.github.io/blog/2014/08/21/using-music-to-learn-a-foreign-language/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-21T10:15:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://askeluv.github.io/blog/2014/08/21/using-music-to-learn-a-foreign-language</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The other day I picked up one of my favourite albums that I hadn&rsquo;t listened to in years, <a href="http://open.spotify.com/album/36fWvul2SzklDegMxkLRyC">Sim by Vanessa da Mata</a>. I don&rsquo;t really speak Portuguese, but I was surprised to find that I knew almost all of the lyrics by heart. After considering it a for a while, I concluded that this wasn&rsquo;t very surprising at all. Just think about how many people around the world have learned their first English words from Beatles songs. (&hellip;or from <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FQt-h753jHI">Mariah Carey songs</a>)</p>

<p>Surely music is a great way to immerse yourself in a new language.</p>

<p>This realisation lead me to an interesting question: <strong>What are the <em>right</em> songs to listen to when you&rsquo;re learning a foreign language?</strong></p>

<p>Putting musical taste aside, I compiled the lyrics of my <a href="http://open.spotify.com/user/askeluv/playlist/5AmbWKvEIVujIFeDRyhZVW">Spanish playlist</a> with the simple purpose of sorting the songs from &ldquo;easy&rdquo; to &ldquo;hard&rdquo;. I want to learn one new song every week &ndash; but I want to learn them in a sensible order, based on my level of Spanish.</p>

<p>The first ranking I came up with was fairly simple: calculate the <em>number of (unique) words</em> per song and sort from low to high. The result looks like this:</p>

<p><img src="/images/spanish_songs_num_words.png" title="Number of Words" ></p>

<p>Of course, this isn&rsquo;t perfect, but it tells us something about the <em>effort</em> involved in learning a song. &ldquo;Vuelvo al Sur&rdquo; will most likely take less time to learn than &ldquo;Na en la nevera&rdquo;. So I placed the former at the top of my playlist.</p>

<p>But what about the actual <em>content</em> of the songs? Surely some songs have a more challenging vocabulary than others?</p>

<p>This is hard to accurately quantify, but we can arrive at a proxy for the &ldquo;language level&rdquo; of a song by considering the &ldquo;word rank&rdquo; of the lyrics. The way we do this is by using a frequency list: ordering words in a language from most used to least used. There is no single &ldquo;golden frequency list&rdquo; for a language, since this is context dependent (the words most used in South Park are different from those in the New York Times).</p>

<p>The frequency list I used is based on movie subtitles <a href="http://invokeit.wordpress.com/frequency-word-lists/">available here</a>, which I believe is fairly close to casual, spoken language.</p>

<p>Now, the idea is to look up each word in a song in the frequency list, and get its rank (its &ldquo;word rank&rdquo;). As an example, in my Spanish frequency list, &ldquo;que&rdquo; is the most common word, which means it has word rank = 1. The word &ldquo;nuevo&rdquo; has word rank = 200, meaning there are 199 words that are more frequent than it, and so on.</p>

<p>We compute the word rank for every (unique) word in a song, and then compute the <em>median</em> word rank.</p>

<p>So what does this tell us? Let&rsquo;s say the median word rank is 500 for a given song. This means that 50% of the words in that song will be among the 500 most frequent words. In other words, a large part of the words are &ldquo;easy&rdquo;, frequent words, so we conclude that the song&rsquo;s lyrics are <em>probably</em> not very hard to understand.</p>

<p>Here are the same songs as above, now ranked by median word rank:</p>

<p><img src="/images/spanish_songs_word_rank.png" title="Median Word Rank" ></p>

<p>Again, &ldquo;Vuelvo al Sur&rdquo; shows up first, so I guess I should really learn that song!</p>

<p>Honestly though, I would have expected the lists to be more similar. It turns out, at least for my playlist, there&rsquo;s not a very strong connection between number of words and the median word rank.</p>

<p>Here are the two metrics on one graph:</p>

<p><img src="/images/spanish_songs_scatter.png" title="Number of Words vs Median Word Rank" >
<em>(Notice how the Alejandro Sanz songs are all clustered together!)</em></p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve divided the songs into four quadrants:</p>

<ol>
<li>Hard songs (upper right corner; <em>Q1</em>)</li>
<li>Niche songs with few words (upper left corner; <em>Q2</em>)</li>
<li>Easy songs (lower left corner; <em>Q3</em>)</li>
<li>General songs with many words (lower right corner; <em>Q4</em>)</li>
</ol>


<p>I might be stretching it with my interpretations of <em>Q2</em> and <em>Q4</em>, but in any case there&rsquo;s a trade-off between them; Q4 means more effort required to learn more useful words, while Q2 means less effort required to learn less useful words.</p>

<p>My personal choice would be to learn <em>Q3</em> (<em>easy</em>) songs first, <em>Q1</em> (<em>hard</em>) songs last, and then randomly pick <em>Q2</em> and <em>Q4</em> in between.</p>

<p><strong>What do you think about this approach to learning languages? And have you ever used music to learn a language?</strong></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
