<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Productivity | Thoughts and Data]]></title>
  <link href="http://askeluv.github.io/blog/categories/productivity/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://askeluv.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-09-18T22:14:53+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://askeluv.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alexander Svanevik]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Using Music To Learn A Foreign Language]]></title>
    <link href="http://askeluv.github.io/blog/2014/08/21/using-music-to-learn-a-foreign-language/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-21T10:15:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://askeluv.github.io/blog/2014/08/21/using-music-to-learn-a-foreign-language</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The other day I picked up one of my favourite albums that I hadn&rsquo;t listened to in years, <a href="http://open.spotify.com/album/36fWvul2SzklDegMxkLRyC">Sim by Vanessa da Mata</a>. I don&rsquo;t really speak Portuguese, but I was surprised to find that I knew almost all of the lyrics by heart. After considering it a for a while, I concluded that this wasn&rsquo;t very surprising at all. Just think about how many people around the world have learned their first English words from Beatles songs. (&hellip;or from <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FQt-h753jHI">Mariah Carey songs</a>)</p>

<p>Surely music is a great way to immerse yourself in a new language.</p>

<p>This realisation lead me to an interesting question: <strong>What are the <em>right</em> songs to listen to when you&rsquo;re learning a foreign language?</strong></p>

<p>Putting musical taste aside, I compiled the lyrics of my <a href="http://open.spotify.com/user/askeluv/playlist/5AmbWKvEIVujIFeDRyhZVW">Spanish playlist</a> with the simple purpose of sorting the songs from &ldquo;easy&rdquo; to &ldquo;hard&rdquo;. I want to learn one new song every week &ndash; but I want to learn them in a sensible order, based on my level of Spanish.</p>

<p>The first ranking I came up with was fairly simple: calculate the <em>number of (unique) words</em> per song and sort from low to high. The result looks like this:</p>

<p><img src="/images/spanish_songs_num_words.png" title="Number of Words" ></p>

<p>Of course, this isn&rsquo;t perfect, but it tells us something about the <em>effort</em> involved in learning a song. &ldquo;Vuelvo al Sur&rdquo; will most likely take less time to learn than &ldquo;Na en la nevera&rdquo;. So I placed the former at the top of my playlist.</p>

<p>But what about the actual <em>content</em> of the songs? Surely some songs have a more challenging vocabulary than others?</p>

<p>This is hard to accurately quantify, but we can arrive at a proxy for the &ldquo;language level&rdquo; of a song by considering the &ldquo;word rank&rdquo; of the lyrics. The way we do this is by using a frequency list: ordering words in a language from most used to least used. There is no single &ldquo;golden frequency list&rdquo; for a language, since this is context dependent (the words most used in South Park are different from those in the New York Times).</p>

<p>The frequency list I used is based on movie subtitles <a href="http://invokeit.wordpress.com/frequency-word-lists/">available here</a>, which I believe is fairly close to casual, spoken language.</p>

<p>Now, the idea is to look up each word in a song in the frequency list, and get its rank (its &ldquo;word rank&rdquo;). As an example, in my Spanish frequency list, &ldquo;que&rdquo; is the most common word, which means it has word rank = 1. The word &ldquo;nuevo&rdquo; has word rank = 200, meaning there are 199 words that are more frequent than it, and so on.</p>

<p>We compute the word rank for every (unique) word in a song, and then compute the <em>median</em> word rank.</p>

<p>So what does this tell us? Let&rsquo;s say the median word rank is 500 for a given song. This means that 50% of the words in that song will be among the 500 most frequent words. In other words, a large part of the words are &ldquo;easy&rdquo;, frequent words, so we conclude that the song&rsquo;s lyrics are <em>probably</em> not very hard to understand.</p>

<p>Here are the same songs as above, now ranked by median word rank:</p>

<p><img src="/images/spanish_songs_word_rank.png" title="Median Word Rank" ></p>

<p>Again, &ldquo;Vuelvo al Sur&rdquo; shows up first, so I guess I should really learn that song!</p>

<p>Honestly though, I would have expected the lists to be more similar. It turns out, at least for my playlist, there&rsquo;s not a very strong connection between number of words and the median word rank.</p>

<p>Here are the two metrics on one graph:</p>

<p><img src="/images/spanish_songs_scatter.png" title="Number of Words vs Median Word Rank" >
<em>(Notice how the Alejandro Sanz songs are all clustered together!)</em></p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve divided the songs into four quadrants:</p>

<ol>
<li>Hard songs (upper right corner; <em>Q1</em>)</li>
<li>Niche songs with few words (upper left corner; <em>Q2</em>)</li>
<li>Easy songs (lower left corner; <em>Q3</em>)</li>
<li>General songs with many words (lower right corner; <em>Q4</em>)</li>
</ol>


<p>I might be stretching it with my interpretations of <em>Q2</em> and <em>Q4</em>, but in any case there&rsquo;s a trade-off between them; Q4 means more effort required to learn more useful words, while Q2 means less effort required to learn less useful words.</p>

<p>My personal choice would be to learn <em>Q3</em> (<em>easy</em>) songs first, <em>Q1</em> (<em>hard</em>) songs last, and then randomly pick <em>Q2</em> and <em>Q4</em> in between.</p>

<p><strong>What do you think about this approach to learning languages? And have you ever used music to learn a language?</strong></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[6 Things I Use Evernote For]]></title>
    <link href="http://askeluv.github.io/blog/2014/04/06/6-things-i-use-evernote-for/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-06T12:44:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://askeluv.github.io/blog/2014/04/06/6-things-i-use-evernote-for</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I use Evernote for &ldquo;Personal Information Management&rdquo; (PIM) aka &ldquo;keeping track of things in your life&rdquo;. Simply put, Evernote is essentially an extension of my brain.</p>

<p>I have two basic requirements for a PIM system:</p>

<ol>
<li>It must be fast and easy to <em>store</em> information</li>
<li>It must be fast and easy to <em>retrieve</em> information</li>
</ol>


<p>Based on these requirements, Evernote is the best PIM tool I&rsquo;ve come across. Still, many people find it difficult to get off the ground with Evernote, so I thought I&rsquo;d share some ideas that I&rsquo;ve built up over the last few months.</p>

<p>Here are <em>6 things I use Evernote for</em>:</p>

<p><strong>1. Physical-notebook substitute</strong></p>

<p>The obvious one. I used to carry Moleskines around, mainly to jot down ideas. In some situations I still do, but now I never have to worry about remembering to bring one with me, and where to store it when I&rsquo;m out of pages.</p>

<p><strong>2. Storing things I find online</strong></p>

<p>Articles, tables, graphs, anything! Just use the <a href="http://evernote.com/webclipper/">Web Clipper plugin</a> and you&rsquo;ll save it in a flash. Recently, I was reading up on <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Classified_advertising">classified advertising</a>, and every article I found on the topic, I tagged with &ldquo;classifieds&rdquo; (in addition to other relevant tags for the article). Now I have a small research bank with highlighted articles on the topic, which I can re-visit when I need to. Again: simple to store, simple to retrieve.</p>

<p>Also, very often I find articles I don&rsquo;t have time to read. Evernote Web Clipper solves this for me in a nice way: Clip, then tag the article with &ldquo;to read&rdquo; (plus other relevant tags), and change the tag to &ldquo;read&rdquo; when you&rsquo;ve read it.</p>

<p><strong>3. Digitizing paper documents</strong></p>

<p>Typical scenario: Find letter in post box. Rip it open. Skim it. Take a photo. Store in Evernote. Tag it. Maybe add a reminder. Then the best part: <em>throw the letter away</em>. Ah. Doesn&rsquo;t that feel nice?!</p>

<p><strong>4. Todos</strong></p>

<p>Evernote is not great for todos in itself, but here&rsquo;s the method I use on my work laptop. Have one note per week, and simply copy that note every new week, moving things you didn&rsquo;t get done last week over to your new note. Here&rsquo;s an example:
<img src="/images/EvernoteTODO_Example.png" title="TODO example" ></p>

<p>A nice bonus feature if you have a tablet: try the presentation view of your last week&rsquo;s completed tasks. Your accomplishments have never looked better!</p>

<p><strong>5. Language learning</strong></p>

<p>I also use Evernote to build vocabulary in foreign languages. The method is simple: again, create one note per week (e.g. &ldquo;French Vocab Week 16&rdquo;), and add new words as you go! Example:
<img src="/images/EvernoteLanguage_Example.png" title="Language example" ></p>

<p>It&rsquo;s a nice way to <em>situate</em> your learning &ndash; that is, you&rsquo;ll be able to register when and where you learned a given word. You can also easily keep track of your learning goals: how many new words did I learn last week, etc.. Also, you can set reminders to notes so you revise the words you jot down.</p>

<p><strong>6. Journal keeping</strong></p>

<p>I&rsquo;m not able to do one entry per day, but if I have 10 minutes to spare at the end of the day, I sometimes spend those minutes on a journal entry. There are a few Evernote journal apps around, but I&rsquo;m fine with just using the title to timestamp my note, then tagging it with &ldquo;journal&rdquo;.</p>

<p><strong>Bonus: Procrastination</strong></p>

<p>Think about it, if you accept you will have some amount of procrastination in your life, why not do something useful? I have tags for retrieving content from my Evernote when I&rsquo;m bored. I already mentioned &ldquo;to read&rdquo;, but &ldquo;ideas&rdquo; is another good one. Reading your own ideas and developing them further is obviously good fun. If you&rsquo;re learning a new language, &ldquo;vocab week&rdquo; is another good tag to have when you&rsquo;d normally be wasting time on your smartphone.</p>

<p><strong>Summary</strong></p>

<p>The common theme of the things listed above is that they all give me a better conscience. I worry less about ideas going lost, not finding useful web content again, letters needing archiving, tasks being forgotten, not spending enough time building vocabulary, my journal being empty, and precious time being wasted on mindless smartphone fiddling.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve mentioned some things I use Evernote for, and I hope you&rsquo;ve learned something useful from reading this. I would love to hear your favourite Evernote tips, so: What do you use Evernote for?</p>

<p><em>Fun fact: this blog post was written on my iPhone while flying from Oslo to Frankfurt using &hellip; Evernote, of course.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
